  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-presentation">
    <title>Presentation</title>

    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	After having defined the structure and technology to use when
	writing this article, there remains the problem of designing
	the presentation. This chapter describes what has been done in
	order to achieve the result you as a reader (hopefully) are seeing.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The goals for the presentation has been clear:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Produce a serious, professional, printed reference.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Produce an online version that can be customized by
	      adding pieces of JavaScript etc. to activate content.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	Both of these include being able to import concept maps in a, 
	for the presentation medium, well adjusted format.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	I have used the <ulink
	url="http://nwalsh.com/docbook/dsssl/">Modular Docbook DSSSL
	Stylesheets</ulink> for the formatting of this article. I have
	had to change two things in the stylesheets:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <sgmltag>Comment</sgmltag> to <sgmltag>Remark</sgmltag>
	      in <filename>dbblock.dsl</filename> and
	      <filename>dbfootn.dsl</filename> in order to support
	      DocBook 4.0.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <quote>Chapter %n</quote> to <quote>Chapter %n,
	      %t</quote> in <filename>dbl1en.dsl</filename>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	Apart from this, I have made some minor customizations to
	adjust the presentation, but these do not affect the
	stylesheets themselves.
      </para>

      
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title>
      <para>
	It has still to be shown that all the wished functionality can
	be easily implemented. The problems still remaining are more
	precisely the following:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The format of concept maps for printing. Optimally, they
	      should be exported to EPS from Conzilla, using the Java
	      Printing API, for example, to allow highest possible
	      resolution (no visible pixels in fonts etc.). That this
	      works is displayed by this example image:
	      <example>
		<title>Figure example</title>
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata format="EPS" fileref="exfig.eps"/>
		  </imageobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata format="GIF" fileref="exfig.gif"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	      </example>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The exact meaning of links in the document in a Conzilla
	      environment: a link to the corresponding concept, a link
	      to the corresponding content, or in some way both?
	      Another problem is the inclusion of suitable JavaScript
	      code to talk to Conzilla. See <xref
	      linkend="ch-externalcoop"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The meaning of a concept map in the online version.  It
	      should probaby be used to start the Conzilla browser on
	      the map, either inline or via a link. As content in a
	      Conzilla environment, they would be importable (and
	      therefore surfable) into the Conzilla browser. the
	      corresponding JavaScript code remains to be written.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
    
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  