  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-structure"> 
    <title>Structure</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	This article is not simply a large piece of text; it is an
	active article intended to demonstrate the very system it
	tries to describe. This chapter describes the structure and
	usage of the article itself, i.e., how it is written and how it
	it intended to be used.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The usage of this article is not limited to printed format. It
	is intended to be used in several different environments:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      As a printed reference.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      As an online reference in HTML, well integrated and
	      linked into the other parts of the <ulink
		url="http://www.nada.kth.se/cid/il/conzilla">Conzilla
		Web pages</ulink>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      As content for a collection of Conzilla maps
	      describing the functionality of the Conzilla browser. This
	      content should actually interact with the Conzilla browser, as
	      the article will contain concept maps to describe its
	      interconnections.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	This combination, in fact, results in a revolutionary new way
	of writing documentation which places high demands on the
	surrounding technology. This same text must not only be able
	to exist and be updateable in three different environments
	simultaneously, but it must also be so well organized that
	the <quote>componentification</quote> necessary for use in the
	Conzilla environment becomes possible.
      </para>

      <para>
	But why is all this complexity worth the while? The real
	advantages comes when the article can be placed in a proper
	context. In our case, this article plugs right into the
	concept maps describing the project in general, the partners,
	etc. It also gives us the possibility of actually linking
	directly from the relevant descriptions into the API reference
	or the philosophical motivation, thereby making the complete
	context of the article immediately accessible. This is the
	revolutionary aspect of this document.
      </para>

      <para>
	Additionally, experimenting with this kind of usage of a
	document is an irreplacible source of experience for the
	Conzilla project.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	The document format is XML with the <glossterm
	linkend="docbook">DocBook</glossterm> XML DTD. It is possible
	to generate plain text, HTML, TeX (and therefore DVI, PS, PDF
	etc.) and other output formats, as well as directly use
	SGML/XML tools like <command>sgrep</command> to extract parts
	of the document.  The document can be used even though it is
	not completed, which allows early web access to and
	experimentation with the parts already completed.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The article consists of structured text and concept maps. The
	text has been structured in chapters, where each large
	concept, and possibly also important associations between
	concepts, has its own chapter. The single sections in each
	chapter serve as content for the concept described, e.g., this
	section describing the architecture of this article serves as
	content for the concept representing this article, under the
	aspect of <quote>architecture</quote> (...read
	slowly). Smaller concepts, not described in a chapter of their
	own, may have content that consists of a smaller part of a
	section describing another concept. For example, this
	paragraph may be the content of the concept <quote>structured
	text</quote> under the aspect of <quote>architecture</quote>.
	The aspects in which we have chosen to separate the content
	are:
	
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&s1;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Describes what is contained within the chapter: the
		limits with respect to other chapters and an
		introduction to the components contained therein.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&s2;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Describes how the design is intended to be used, i.e.,
		the possible uses and wanted functionality which have
		influenced the design.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&s3;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Describes the internals of the present design, i.e.,
		how we manage to produce the wanted functionality.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&s4;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Discusses the usage of the current design. Presents the
		motivations for the design and discusses previous designs
		and why they were abandoned, as well as alternative designs
		that have been considered. Points to problems in the
		present design and design goals for the future.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The concept maps are different things in different output
	formats. In printed form, they are simply pictures, while
	online, they will be used to interact with Conzilla.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title> 
      <para>
	The only reasonable choice as document format that adheres
	sufficiently to the principles of polyvalence and structure is
	XML (or SGML, of course). The choice of DocBook as DTD is based
	on its status as a growing and well-proven standard for
	technical documentation.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	As this is the first reference work prepared to be used
	directly in a Conzilla environment, it is interesting to note
	the experience it has given, as we hope that the article may
	form a model for how to write reference documentation with the
	help of Conzilla. For a technical document like this, that
	tries to be very systematic in its descriptions, it is impossible
	to even start considering what to write before having decided
	under which aspects to describe the concepts, as these
	represent the classification of information. Therefore, it is
	very much worth it to spend time analyzing the wanted
	aspects. This is in turn impossible until you have an idea of
	which concepts you want to include. So the process of writing
	becomes:
	
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Draw all the concept maps (or nearly all) that you
	      want to include. Decide which concept are worthy their own
	      chapters. This becomes the scope and the structure of the
	      article.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Consider the aspects you want to describe. This
	      reflects the depth and target audience for the article.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Decide the order of chapters and possible appendices.
	      This is important for the logical structure of the article. 
	      Without the right linear order, it becomes unbearable to
	      read.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	Please note that this <quote>bondage &amp;
	discipline</quote><footnote><para>Attributed to Eric
	S. Raymond</para></footnote> way of writing is applicable
	primarily to reference documentation. Other types of
	documentation, such as reports etc. need another, freer style
	of writing. This does of course not stop them from being
	introduced in a Conzilla environment as well. It just lessens
	the level of structure.
      </para>
      
    </section>
  </chapter>
   
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  