  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-content">
    <title>Content</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	If neurons deal with the contextual organization of
	information, it is the content that contains the information
	that we organize. While concepts deal with the inner, mental
	world, content represents the link to the outer world of text,
	images and sound; the world of media and communication. The
	activation of content is one of the most important motivations
	for the creation of context at all.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	Content consists of explanations, examples and definitions of
	concepts used in learning environments, representing different
	aspects of the concept in question. It may also consist of
	physical or digital resources that have a representation in
	the system for lexical purposes. So the definition of content
	consists of two parts:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Designing a representation of a piece of content in
	      the system. This must include meta-data on the content, such
	      as type information, and the location of digital content or
	      the identification of physical content. The idea is that you
	      should be able to search for and choose content without having
	      seen the content itself, only this description.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Associating such a content description with a concept
	      or other type of neuron.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The ideas for the usage of content and aspects are carefully
	described in <citation>cid52</citation>, and will therefore
	not be repeated here.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	The representation in the system of a piece of content is made
	completely inside the existing system by defining a neuron
	type <literal>content-description</literal> and letting each
	piece of content be represented by a neuron of this type. This
	type has the following attributes:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      degree zero, i.e., no axons. This reflects the fact
	      that this really is an atomic object in the system (even
	      though perhaps not outside).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      two data tags: <literal>URI</literal>, the value of
	      which is the location of the content, and
	      <literal>MIMEType</literal>, giving a MIME type for the
	      object.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	This way we know where and what the content is. All other
	information as to what the content is about, for whom it is
	suitable etc. must be specified in the meta-data, with
	standardized tags.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	These neurons can then be linked to by other neurons just as
	usual, thereby fully incorporating the content into the
	system.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	To allow the content neurons to be treated as the content of a
	specific concept, we use the axon type
	<literal>content</literal> of concepts, relations etc., to
	point to content description neurons. The content descriptions
	found at the other end of such an axon are interpreted as the
	content of that neuron.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section id="ch-content-4">
      <title>&s4;</title>
      <para>
	The choice of MIME as a representation of type
	information for content follows very similar lines to the
	choice of URI as identifier format:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The existing MIME types immediately usable:
	      <literal>text/plain</literal>,
	      <literal>image/jpeg</literal> etc., as well as the
	      probability of useful future standard types. MIME types
	      have been proved useful and functional, not only in mail
	      attachments, but notably also in the HTTP protocol, and
	      seem to be the de facto standard for digital types.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The existing standardized encoding in ASCII text,
	      making it universally usable, as well as the support in
	      different programming environments that support HTTP. A not
	      small part of this point is that users are actually a bit used
	      to this type of identifiers.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The hierarchical structure of the types is
	      interesting, but not as important as for URIs.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The possibility of defining your own types. In fact, it
	      would not pose any problem to define types for physical
	      resources as well. As an example: combined with a URI
	      protocol designed for this purpose, one could define the
	      type <literal>physical/postal-address</literal> with the
	      URI pointing to a postal address.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<remark>Add something about Dublin Core resource types.</remark>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It is not difficult to argue that both the type and the
	location actually belongs in
	meta-data. This will be considered.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It may seem as a violation of the design principles for axons
	to let the content be an axon in many different types of
	neurons, as the content may not seem <quote>essential for its
	existence</quote>. This line of argumentation clearly has its points,
	and it is admitted that the implemented solution may not be
	the cleanest one; one could for example want another neuron
	linking a neuron to its content, to make both the neuron and
	the content independent of the link between them (this is why
	generalizations, for example, are separate neurons). This
	would allow you to add content to neurons you cannot modify, a
	not uninteresting feature.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	On the other hand, there are two points speaking for our
	solution. The first is purely philosophical; consider that
	concepts actually are <quote>representations of a group of
	phenomena</quote> (see <citation>cid17</citation>), where the
	collection of content actually tries to describe the
	phenomena; it may after all seem that this content is
	essential for the existence of the concept, as the concept is
	a representation of what these pieces of content have in
	common.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The second point is that the idea of content is so central to
	the browser that one would almost want to create a completely
	separate structure much resembling the axon idea, solely in
	order to
	simplify the introduction of content. To reuse the existing
	functionality then seems like the better way to go. Ideas in
	this area would, however, be much appreciated.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It is interesting to note that
	<literal>content-description</literal> is one of the single
	neuron types that are completely self-contained from this
	point of view, as such a neuron itself does not contain any
	content. As a remark it might be interesting to allow
	<quote>content collections</quote> to facilitate multiple
	narration techniques, but that is another story.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The content description was originally a component on its own,
	as the system at that time was not general enough to allow it
	to be represented by the other components of the time. This
	had the sad consequence that the content was not really
	represented in the system as something possible to link to in
	any other way than as content. The current system introduces
	content as a full-worthy neuron which makes it possible to
	actually describe relations between content as concept maps as
	well as, as described above, to represent the relation of
	being content of a concept without having to introduce any new
	structures into the system. This has had further consequences
	in connection with <link linkend="ch-filters">Filters</link>.
      </para>

      <para>
	One problem with content arises when you try to link into a
	complex piece of content, such as this article. Currently, you
	will need to create one separate content description for each
	section you want to link to, which quickly becomes somewhat
	cumbersome, and in some way seems necessary. Instead, one could
	imagine putting extra information into the content role in the
	neurons having a piece of this articla as content. This way,
	this article would be represented by a single content
	description, and a link to this section could be a content
	axon with data
	<literal>urimodifier="ch-content-4.html"</literal><footnote>
	<para>The file name of this section</para></footnote>, which
	would be a URI relative to the URI given in the content
	description. Note that this URI would (probably) necessarily
	be relative, but that it also may contain fragment
	identifiers. Other types of content-displayer-specific
	modifying are perfectly imaginable, such as command-line
	arguments for an application etc.
      </para>

      <para>
	Note, however, that any type of meta-data modifying would be
	impossible (and unwanted). Thus, using such a system for this
	article would still not be a good idea, as each section needs
	separate meta-data markup to enable filtering. This could all be a
	server-side problem of generating content descriptions on the
	fly from their identifiers.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  