  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-contentdisp">
    <title>The Content Displayer</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	The content displayer completes the browser with a method of
	accessing content, which, after all, is one of the two
	fundamental browsing steps. It contains the methods for viewing
	and interacting with content, as well as the application
	of filters on content.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The content displayer has the following responsabilities, all
	described in detail in <citation>cid52</citation>:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Use the specified filters to sort content for a neuron
	      into aspects, and present the result of this sorting to
	      the user.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Present content according to the user choice. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the content is another concept map, allow the
	      <quote>contextification</quote> of this map, meaning
	      that the map is <quote>sucked in</quote> into the
	      browser to allow it to be browsed (and edited, of course).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>

      <para>
	The content is sorted according to the filter specified in the
	concept map, or if the neuron itself specifies a filter, this
	filter is used. The sorting is displayed as a meny with
	submenus as outlined in <xref linkend="ch-filters"/>, and when
	a leaf is selected, the contents reaching this leaf are
	listed, and the user is allowed to choose among them.
      </para>

      <para>
	After having chosen a content to view, the content displaying
	is multiplexed with respect to the MIME type of the
	content. The MIME type
	<literal>application/x-conceptmap</literal> is displayed using
	a simple map displaying window without any tools (and is thus
	completely uninteractive). It can still be contextified using
	a tool in the originating map. Other MIME types are handled by
	a web browser. There are two possibilites:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Conzilla runs as an applet in a web browser. Then a
	      frame named <literal>content</literal> is used to
	      display the content.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Conzilla runs as an independent application. Then
	      Conzilla tries to use a running browser to display
	      content.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title>
      <para>
	The content displaying is an area where there are many future
	possibilities when it comes to increased interaction with
	content. They are discussed in <xref
	linkend="ch-externalcoop"/>.
      </para>

      <para>
	It is worth noting that we have only implemented support for
	Netscape Communicator as external content displayer. Adding
	further support is, however, trivial. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The URI given in the content description, and which is used to
	locate content, may be of any general form. When viewing a
	concept map as content, the displaying is handled by Conzilla
	itself, and thus the complete machinery of
	<literal>urn:path:</literal> resolving is used. Unfortunately,
	this is not used for other types of content. Instead, it is up
	to the web browser used to interpret the URI. This could cause
	problems in the future. See further <xref
	  linkend="ch-externalcoop"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  