  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-editor">
    <title>The Editor</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	The editor is a fundamental part of the prototype, as it
	(ideally) hides from the user all the technical details of
	constructing neurons and maps. But the editor functions are
	useful for more than that; it can also be used to increase the
	level of interactivity of concept maps.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The editor should fulfil the following goals:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should be independent of the browser in the sense
	      that the browser should work without it.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should be independent of the data format the edited
	      component happens to use.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should allow the editing of all fields in editable
	      neurons and conceptmaps, and possibly neuron types. This
	      editing should be graphical or aided by graphical hints
	      if possible.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should be responsible for the saving of changes.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	The editor is implemented directly in the browser system, so
	that you are able to edit a map in the very same window you
	use for browsing it.
      </para>

      <para>
	The editor is implemented using tools that attach mouse and
	key listeners to the map graphics elements. In turn, when
	editing, the editor modifies the actual concept map and neuron
	objects, and the map display will be automatically updated
	using property change listeners.
      </para>

      <para>
	The editor consists of three main parts:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The map editor, which does all the graphical editing of
	      conceptmaps.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The neuron editor, which does all the editing of
	      neurons.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A metadata editor, which edits metadata for neurons and
	      for concept maps. This is currently not functional. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title>
      <para>
	The intense use of listener mechanism has made it possible to
	make the edit functionality one tool amongst others. As the
	editor is heavily dependent on user interaction, and therefore
	user interface design, it is expected that it will develop
	considerably in the way it works with the edited
	elements. Thus, the current method of implementation ensures
	minimal impact on other parts of the code, notably the
	browser.
      </para>

      <para>
	The separation of editing functionality is necessary because
	being able to edit a neuron directly in the concept map would most
	probably be confusing, as one actually edits different
	objects.
      </para> 

      <para>
	It is noted that we have no method of creating and editing
	neuron types. This should be added.
      </para>

      <para>
	Also note that the functionality in the editor for moving and
	otherwise manipulating concept maps could be used to increase
	the interactivity of concept maps in the sense described in
	<xref linkend="ch-browser-dd"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  