  <!-- $Id$ -->
  
  <chapter id="ch-neurons">
    <title>Neurons and Neuron Types</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	The neuron and neuron type objects define what we mean by a
	concept and a relation, and how we have chosen to describe
	them, and is therefore the part of the Conzilla design that
	makes it a concept browser.  Neurons and neuron types
	constitute the logical network of concepts and relations, not
	tied to a certain visual presentation.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The question of how to represent concepts and their relations is
	a difficult one, and much of the design work has therefore
	gone into figuring out what, exactly, we want to use them for.
	In the end, these are the important design goals we have
	considered:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Existing concepts and associations must be
	      incorporable in any concept maps, i.e., must be independent of
	      any specific concept map. New associations must be able to
	      connect concepts located anywhere, i.e., it must not be
	      necessary to change the associated concepts. This is to allow
	      reuse of components on a global basis.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The concepts and associations must be typed. For
	      associations, the motivation is clear: To be able to search
	      for concepts having a certain relation to a given concept, the
	      types of the associations must be known. For concepts, it is
	      not that clear. In fact, the motivation is that one may want
	      to have other types of objects represented in the system, such
	      as events or states (to be able to draw activity diagrams), and
	      these objects are not strictly concepts.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Associations must be able to associate any number of
	      concepts. This is motivated by the existence in UML of
	      n-ary associations and in other relational systems such
	      as <classname>CORBA::RelationShips</classname> of
	      similar constructs. In reality, this reflects the need
	      to represent relations such as a book loan, which has
	      three parties: the loaner, the library and the book.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Association should preferably be able to relate
	      associations to oneanother. It is not at all uncommon to
	      encounter an association that is very much related to
	      another one, and this must be expressible.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section id="ch-neurons-3">
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	The design consists of two types of components: neurons and
	neuron types. To understand the terms used here, let us define
	a few terms that are often used when discussing associations
	(The terminology is taken from
	<classname>CORBA::Relationships</classname>, as described in
	<citation>corbarelationships</citation>):
	
	<glosslist>
	  <glossentry>
	    <glossterm>role</glossterm>
	    <glossdef>
	      <para>
		is an end of the association. We say that a concept
		<quote>plays a role</quote> in the association. Each
		role is of a certain <glossterm>role type</glossterm>,
		and an association may
		be able to hold roles of several different role types.
	      </para>
	    </glossdef>
	  </glossentry>
	  
	  <glossentry>
	    <glossterm>degree or arity</glossterm>
	    <glossdef>
	      <para>
		is the number of different role types that a role in an
		association can be of. In the case of a generalization
		there are only two role types: the general and the
		specific.  We can imagine more complicated cases. Take
		a book loan as an example. There are three role types
		involved: the <type>person</type> loaning the book,
		the <type>library</type> and a number of
		<type>book</type>s. So this association has degree
		three.
	      </para>
	    </glossdef>
	  </glossentry>
	  
	  <glossentry>
	    <glossterm>multiplicity</glossterm>
	    <glossdef>
	      <para>
		of a role type is the number of concepts that play
		roles of that role type in an association. In the book
		loan example, one person can loan two books at the
		same time from a library. So the multiplicity of the
		<type>book</type> role type in this book loan is
		two. The <emphasis>allowed</emphasis> multiplicity of
		the book role type may, however, be much larger, and
		maybe even unlimited.
	      </para>
	    </glossdef>
	  </glossentry>
	</glosslist>
      </para>
      
      <section>
	<title>Neuron</title>
	<para>
	  Neurons represent both associations and concepts, as well as
	  other types of objects needed in other types of diagrams, such
	  as events or states. A neuron has the following attributes:
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A type, in the form of a reference to (i.e., the
		identifier of) a neuron type.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A number of meta-data tag-value pairs (as all
		database components have).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A number of <quote>data</quote> tag-value pairs. Data
		allows concepts and associations to actually contain
		information that are inherent to their type. For
		example, a neuron of the type <literal>historical event</literal> may be equipped with an historical
		date.  This is what makes the database we are
		designing actually contain data.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A number of <quote>axons</quote>, where each axons
		points to another neuron via its identifier. This
		corresponds to roles for associations, and so each
		axon has a type and a multiplicity (as an interval
		between zero and infinity), reflecting the number of
		objects that the other side represents. For example,
		neurons that represent aggregations have axons of the
		types <literal>part</literal> and
		<literal>aggregate</literal> representing the two ends
		in this association. If one axon of the type
		<literal>aggregate</literal> points to the concept
		<literal>bicycle</literal>, and another of the type
		<literal>part</literal> points to the concept
		<literal>wheel</literal>, the former will have
		multiplicity one, while the latter will have the
		multiplicity interval one to four (perhaps),
		describing the fact that bicycles have one, two,
		three, or four wheels. Note that axons are still
		called <quote>roles</quote> in the current
		implementation, even if this is expected to change.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		An enumeration of neurons that may have axons
		pointing to this neuron. This is a hint list only, i.e.,
		neither obligating nor exhaustive.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para id="ch-neurons-3-filter">
	  Further, a neuron may contain the following meta-data tags
	  in addition to standard resource tags:
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Filter</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Gives the identifier of a <link
		  linkend="ch-filters">filter</link> to be used to sort
		  the content of this neuron.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</para>
      </section>
      
      
      <section>
	<title>Neuron types</title>
	<para>
	  Neuron types defines the allowed values of the different
	  attributes of a neuron, and therefore is what distinguishes
	  concepts from associations and other sorts of neurons. A
	  neuron type also contains hints as to how objects of the type
	  are to be presented visually. The generic attributes are:
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A number of meta-data tag-value pairs (as all
		database components have).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		An enumeration of the allowed data tags.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		An enumeration of the allowed axon types, each with
		their own allowed multiplicity (as an interval between zero
		and infinity).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  A neuron is not allowed to use other data tags or axons types
	  than these declared in its type. This is partially enforced in
	  the current implementation; not, however, on the database
	  level, but only when creating or modifying neurons.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  The visual attributes are grounded on the assumption that the
	  presentation of a neuron consists of a cell body and the
	  axons. A concept will not have any axons, and is therefore
	  represented only by the body, while associations in general
	  have no visible body, but may very well have if they are
	  important objects in themselves. The attributes in the current
	  implementation are:
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Attributes for the axons: a thickness between 1 and 10
		as well as a line type, such as
		<literal>continuous</literal>,
		<literal>broken</literal>, etc., as well as attributes
		describing how the end of the axons, the head, should
		look. There is a head type, e.g.,
		<literal>arrow</literal>, <literal>diamond</literal>,
		as well as a size parameter between 1 and
		10. It is also possible to specify if the head should
		be filled or not.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Attributes for the body: a box type, which is a string
		describing the shape of the body, such as
		<literal>rectangle</literal>,
		<literal>ellipse</literal>, etc. There is also the
		possibility of connecting the body with the axons with
		the help of a line, which has the same
		attributes as the axon lines above.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  The application is free to interpret these characteristics in
	  the way it finds suitable for the presentation medium.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title>

      <para>
	The motivation behind the terminology <quote>neuron</quote> is
	the following: As what we have designed is a generalization of both
	concepts and associations, and indeed may be used to represent
	even other things, neither of these names would be
	appropriate. A neuron, on the other hand, is an entity which
	connects other neurons with each other using axons<footnote>
	  <para>
	    and dendrites, of course. But all analogies have their problems...
	  </para>
	</footnote>, and thus serves both as link and as the subject
	of links. Our neurons connect to form a globally
	interconnected <quote>neural network</quote>, which we
	visualize using computer tomography sections, that we call
	concept-maps (which, however, may not be entirely in line with
	the metaphor).
      </para>
      
      <para>
	This is a very abstract picture, but this is what makes it
	possible to describe the different types of relations we want
	to describe. It is, we believe, an interesting new way of
	representing graphs that, in effect, comes down to assigning
	an owner to each edge in the graph among the two nodes it is
	connecting.
      </para>

      <para>
	Note that when we say <quote>neuron</quote>, we mean any
	object represented by a neuron, while the word
	<quote>concept</quote> is only used to talk about neurons that
	represent concepts or similar objects.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It has been a long way before we have reached the current
	design. Our first attempt at creating the structure, carefully
	described in <citation>cid53</citation> lead to failure on
	several points:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      We were fixated on the ideas of concept and
	      association, and therefore failed too see how we were to
	      expand the system to include other types of object to be able
	      to draw, for example, activity diagrams. This also led to an
	      underestimation of the importance of
	      associations. Remember what <author>
		<firstname>Henri</firstname>
		<surname>Poincaré</surname></author> said:
	      
	      <blockquote>
		<para>
		  The aim of science is not things themselves - as the
		  dogmatists in their simplicity imagine - but the
		  relations between things. Outside those relations there
		  is no reality knowable.
		</para>
	      </blockquote>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Associations were not separate components, but were
	      instead each included in a concept, leading to severe problems
	      and complexity when wanting to associate external
	      concepts.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Associations were only allowed to be of degree
	      exactly two, which was motivated by the fact that the most
	      common associations were of degree two, as well as by the fact
	      that the MOF actually had the same restriction (which we now
	      consider a severe defect in the MOF). In fact, higher degree
	      association can be simulated by introducing a new concept
	      acting as middle point. However, the current solution results
	      in a much cleaner and more natural system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Associations had no type, resulting in problems when
	      attaching common appearances to the same sort of associations,
	      as well as problems of standardization when wanting to
	      introduce new sorts of associations.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	All of these problems were clear to us even before we had
	finished the implementation of the first Conzilla prototype,
	and the solution described here was already on the drawing
	board. By contrast, we strongly believe in the current system
	design. The system has proved itself to work very
	well in unexpected circumstances.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The elimination of the fundamental difference between a
	concept and an association actually has philosophical
	consequences that are important. It succeeds in elevating
	associations to the same status as have concepts. But it also
	has technical consequences, in the sense that everything you
	can do with a concept, you can automatically do with an
	association. For example, when implementing the assigning of
	content to concepts to aid in explaining them, this becomes
	an automatic feature of associations as well, which is not
	insignificant! This allows, namely, the explanation of
	associations by the same means, which results in exactly the
	emphasis on the relations between things that we were
	searching.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It is expected that map designers in different areas construct
	their own neuron types for use in their own situations, but it
	is also expected that there will be a considerable amount of
	work dedicated to the standardization of types, as this is
	what allows large-scale searching. Regrettably, we have not
	ourselves done much work in this direction, and it is clear to
	us that before this design is set in stone, we will have to
	try to encode knowledge from several disciplines in the system
	so as to be sure that it is actually possible and that the
	system is flexible enough to cover all relevant needs.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	When considering which axon types a new neuron type should
	have, the idea is that axons connect neurons with the neurons
	that are essential for its existence. As an example, a
	generalization does not exist before you have something to
	generalize and something to specialize, which is why it has
	degree two, while a concept exists by itself and therefore has
	degree zero (See further <xref linkend="ch-content"/>,
	however). The same reasoning holds for data as well: it
	represents information without which the neuron does not
	exist. The difference is that the information given by a data
	tag is not represented by another neuron (meta-data, on the
	other hand, is not information internal to the neuron, but
	external information).
      </para>
      
      <para>
	We plan to allow data tags in each axon as well. This is
	debatable, but actually simplifies many design tasks. The
	reason to want data tags in axons is to avoid having to
	construct an extra layer of neurons between the neuron and the
	neurons it links to. For example, you may consider
	representing a sequence of events by letting them be attached
	to an <literal>event-sequence</literal> neuron. Then you
	realize that being connected by axons from this neuron
	prohibits you from marking the events with the time when they
	happened, and so you may consider adding the time information
	to the axons (as it is impossible to add it to the events
	themselves; they take part in several different
	sequences). The alternative would be lifting the relation to
	neuron status, by defining a
	<literal>event-occurrence</literal> neuron type, connected to
	the event with an axon and with the time it occurred as
	data. Then the event-sequence neuron may connect to this
	neuron instead. It is not at all clear which solution is the
	right one for this case, as this in fact depends on if you
	will need to do one of the following things with the
	<literal>event-occurrence</literal>:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Allow it to have meta-data.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>      
	      Link to it from another neuron, or in any way use it
	      separately.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>      
	      Link it to content explaining it.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Indeed, if you need to do one of the above, the
	<literal>event-occurrence</literal> clearly needs to be a
	neuron on its own. It is clear that not every relation can be
	a neuron, as this would lead to infinite recursion. The above
	points summarize the limit when a relation can be represented
	by an axon. Thus, the example shows the importance of
	considering carefully which neuron types you need.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The remaining problems in the design, in need of discussion,
	include:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>	  
	      A more serious standardization of the visual
	      attributes, as well as usage experiments to examine the
	      relevance of the different attributes.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A discussion of the role of the neuron type. Should
	      you be able to inherit types? Which types are standard, and
	      what identifiers should they have? Is the type an attribute of
	      the neuron, or should it not in fact be part of the meta-data?
	      Should the restrictions in the type be enforced by the system
	      in some way?
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      A discussion of the role of multiplicity. Is the
	      concept well defined and useful, and is the design the right?
	      Perhaps it should be incorporated in the future data tags of
	      the axons?
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Where should meta-data be located? Is it really
	      necessary to download it together with the neuron?
	      Perhaps a separate <quote>meta-data</quote> component is
	      the solution.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      How are you supposed to find all the axons that point
	      to a given neuron? Part of a solution is given by the hint
	      list contained in each neuron. But if you add a link to a
	      neuron that you cannot modify, this does not help much. It
	      becomes obvious that in the future, a standardized catalogue
	      function will be necessary.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  
  
  