  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapter id="ch-prototype">
    <title>The Conzilla Prototype</title>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s1;</title>
      <para>
	The Conzilla browser is the first prototype implementation of
	a conceptual brower, and therefore forms the testbed for all
	our ideas concerning concept browsing. Thus, what is described
	here should not be understood as implementation specifications
	for future browsers, but rather as proof of concept (no pun
	intended) and as a source for inspiration. But still, nobody
	would be happier than us if the prototype turned out to be
	practically usable.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s2;</title>
      <para>
	The Conzilla browser has been designed with several thoughts
	in mind:

        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The choice of programming environment must be done
	      with care. This is discussed in <xref
		linkend="ch-environment"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
       
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should be based on a library dealing only with the
	      representation of the components and the different data
	      formats, to allow the reuse of this code in different
	      situations. This is discussed in <xref
		linkend="ch-classlib"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
          
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It should adhere to exiting standards to the largest amount
	      possible. By following standards we ensure
	      compatibility now and in the future, but we also
	      increase the amount of existing implementations
	      immediately usable.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Trying not to tie the browser to a certain platform is a
	      necessary design principle to ensure that the design of the
	      database structure does not itself become platform
	      dependent, something which could obviously not be accepted.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
       
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A good separation between the different components
	      will be necessary, to simplify replacing them with new
	      implementations, something that will happen.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s3;</title>
      <para>
	The choice of programming environment is desribed in <xref
	  linkend="ch-environment"/>,
	while the base library is described in <xref
	  linkend="ch-classlib"/>. The different
	parts of the browser are:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The browser itself, containing the map management and
	      browsing functions. It is described in <xref
		linkend="ch-browser"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The editor, used to construct neurons and maps
	      graphically. It is described in <xref
		linkend="ch-editor"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
       
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The library, used to maintain collections of neurons
	      for purposes such as history, bookmarks etc. It is
	      described in <xref linkend="ch-library"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The content sorting and viewing mechanisms. They are
	      described in <xref linkend="ch-contentdisp"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Each of the above are separate and, to the greatest extent
	possible, independent entities.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>&s4;</title>
      <para>
	The browser is an ever changing construct, and necessarily so.
	Changes in specifications, user design wishes, and
	implementation design has forced several rewrites of
	fundamental components. This way, it has evolved into a highly
	modular structure to allow these changes to take place without
	needing to redesign other parts.
      </para>

      <para>
	This structure is mostly inspired by technical needs. There
	has been too few user studies, something that should be
	initiated as soon as possible as it could profoundly affect
	the design of certain parts.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Future additions include adding a help desk system, as
	described in <citation>cid52</citation>. Hopefully, this
	can be done without affecting the current code.
      </para>

      <para>
	The name <quote>Conzilla</quote> has been inspired by the
	<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla</ulink> browser,
	with the twist that it browses concepts. The interpretation
	<quote>CONZeptual ILLuminAtor</quote> has been suggested, and
	hereby, a relation with <quote>concilience</quote><footnote>
	<para>As used by Edward O. Wilson in
	<citation>wilson</citation></para>
	</footnote>
	is proposed.<remark>Add citation...</remark>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  