  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <section>
      <title>Conzilla</title>

      <para>
	Conzilla<footnote>
	  <para>This section was adapted from
	    <citation>cid52</citation>.
	  </para>
	</footnote>
	is the first incarnation of the concept browser idea
	as developed by the Garden of Knowledge project at <glossterm
	  linkend="cid">Centre for User Oriented IT-design,
	  CID</glossterm>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	CID is an interdisciplinary research group and
	academy-industry collaboration centre, which is located at the
	department of Numerical Analysis and Computing Science (NADA)
	at <glossterm linkend="kth">KTH</glossterm>, Stockholm. At
	CID, there is a unique blend of knowledge from fields such as
	pedagogy, computer science, mathematics, art and design as
	well as cognitive and behavioral science. CID is engaged in a
	multitude of projects that aim to develop Information and
	Communication Technology based tools of various kinds.
      </para>

      <para>
	Today, the activities at CID are divided into three major
	areas of research and development called respectively Smart
	Things and Environments, Digital Worlds and Interactive
	Learning Environments. The initial project within the latter
	field was the Garden of Knowledge (GoK) project, which was
	initiated by Ambjörn Naeve in 1996.
      </para>

      <para>
	The Garden of Knowledge is the name of a multi-mediated
	learning-tool project which aims to develop IT-supported
	methods to create an interdisciplinary understanding of the
	perceptual and conceptual world, and to develop an educational
	framework for the creation of interactive and individualized
	forms of learning experiences.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Conzilla is the first prototype of the idea of a
	<quote>concept browser</quote>, which is currently under
	continuous development at CID. In short, a concept browser
	tries to present the conceptual relationships between a set
	of concepts in the form of surfable <quote>concept
	maps</quote>, and to allow the surfer to, separately, engage
	in content describing these concepts. The details and the
	merits of this idea are thoroughly described in
	<citation>cid52</citation>, and there is no room here to
	further discuss this.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>This article</title>

      <para>
	This article is the definitive reference to the design of the
        Conzilla browser, version 1.0, for anyone interested in the
	functionality of the system. The content of this article has
	three main goals:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      To give a description of the technical functionality and
	      architecture of the Conzilla browser, in as much detail
	      as possible without entering into implementation
	      details, philosophical discussions or user interface
	      issues. This includes defining all important interfaces
	      and standards as well as describing the level of
	      fulfillance of the design goals. The purpose is to make
	      it possible even for outsiders to understand the design
	      and this way be able to contribute to the design
	      discussion and development without being programmers.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      To give important examples and explanations of uses
	      that have influenced and motivated the design.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      To give a picture of the design development. This
	      involves presenting previous designs and why they were
	      abandoned, as well as alternative designs that have been
	      considered. As well, the goal is to describe the known
	      problems of the present design and ideas for future
	      designs that were in our minds while building the
	      product. This way, it is much easier to understand the
	      present design and very incomplete design ideas that
	      have influenced it. It is also an important starting
	      point for discussions of future design goals.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	Thus, it is intended to be non-technical in the sense of not
	being a programming reference, and non-philosophical in the
	sense of not trying to motivate in other ways than technical
	and functional. Still, it is extremely useful as a starting
	point for any programmer interested in the project, and
	indispensable for anyone interested in how we manage to
	fulfill the design goals and what sort of beast Conzilla
	really is. It is, however, not a user manual; in fact, most
	users will be very happy not to know the details presented
	here.
      </para>

      <para>
	Please note that this article is not just a passive piece of
	text. It takes an active part of the Conzilla project as an
	example of the usage of the system. The technical design and
	functionality is described in <link
	  linkend="article">Part IV, <emphasis>Technical
	    design of the article.</emphasis></link>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <para>
	I would like to thank the project initiator, Ambjörn Naeve,
	for the support he has given me during the writing of this
	article, and for making it possible at all. His high
	philosophical demands has driven not only the process of
	contructing this work, but also the whole design it describes.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	An important part has of course been played by Matthias
	Palmér, the co-designer of most of what is described here, and
	main designer of some. His comments have been worth gold.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	I also want to thank CID and the people involved in the Garden
	of Knowledge project there: Bosse Westerlund, Hans Melkersson
	and all the others, who work intensively to give the project the
	cross-disciplinary form it is intended to have.
      </para>

      <para>
	I would like to thank Anna Petersson, who lent us part of her
	creative powers and succeeded in creating the name of our
	browser, Conzilla. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Lastly, I want to thank Linus Torvalds for giving us Linux,
	as well as the whole free software community and the GNU project for
	letting me use a superior SGML/XML authoring environment.
      </para>
    </section>
  </preface>


  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-default-dtd-file:"docbookx.ced"
  End:
  -->
  